<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An anti-remonstrance to the late humble remonstrance to the high court of Parliament</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1641</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 25 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 15 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A25670</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing A3512</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R13045</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12934442</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12934442</idno>
            <idno type="VID">95736</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A25670)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 95736)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 730:11)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An anti-remonstrance to the late humble remonstrance to the high court of Parliament</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <editionStmt>
                  <edition>The second edition, enlarged.</edition>
               </editionStmt>
               <extent>[2], 15 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London? :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1641.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Hall, Joseph, 1574-1656. --  Humble remonstrance to the high court of Parliament.</term>
               <term>Church of England --  Bishops.</term>
               <term>Episcopacy.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:95736:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:95736:1"/>
            <p>AN ANTI-RE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>MONSTRANCE, TO THE LATE HVMBLE REMON<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>STRANCE TO THE HIGH COVRT OF PARLIAMENT.</p>
            <p>The ſecond Edition, enlarged.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Printed Anno</hi> 1641.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="answer">
            <pb facs="tcp:95736:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:95736:2"/>
            <head>AN ANTI-RENON<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>STRANCE TO THE LATE HVMBLE REMONSTRANCE to the High Court of Parliament.</head>
            <p>THeſe few Leaves of Paper breake on through, after the humble re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrance, with leſſe noyle, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of leſſe bulke; and not ſtuffed with the huskes of a bare pleaſing ſpeech, but preſented to your view with more ſubſtance then Rethorique, and with more things then words, and ſuch as I hope will plucke off the vizard of dutifull Sonne from the Authour of the Remonſtrance, or make his Mother little behol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to him for his adviſe. Yee are not ignorant of the great diſtractions, oppoſitions, and of the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſity of affections and feares of the people of the whole land about the event of the Churches reformation in hand: for indeede ſome out of a zeale, ſomewhat inconſiderate doe cry downe E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſcopacy as Antichriſtian. Others very mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate crave and wiſh earneſtly, Epiſcopacy were
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:95736:3"/>reformed and purged from the Romiſh and Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rannicall governement that incumbers it, and which ſince the laſt reformation in King <hi>Edward</hi> the ſixth dayes, no free Parliament yet was ſo hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py as to redreſſe: Againe, a third kind of men carried by a contrary winde, maintaine Epiſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacy to bee by Divine right, not ſo much as na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming that apple of diſcord, nor mentioning the maine thing which is ſo much ſtood upon, which is not that Epiſcopacie is either of Divine right or not, for if (as the Author of the remon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrance acknowledgeth,) a Church may ſtand without Epiſcopacie, it matters not much, which of theſe two opinions is held: but the maine point debated lyes in this aſſertion, that <hi>Epiſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall government, as it is eſtabliſhed in England is moſt diſagreeable to Chriſt and the Apostles inſtitution, and to the rites and conſtitutions of the primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Church, and makes a part of the myſterie of iniquitie, which the Roman Church for many hundred yeares in England hath had the greateſt ſhare in.</hi> Likewiſe the favourers of the humble remon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrance traduce as libellers the oppoſers of that tenet of <hi>Epiſcopacie</hi> by Divine right, and of the corruptions that attend Epiſcopacie, as it is eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed in <hi>England.</hi> Theſe diſtractions and op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions being ſuch; may it pleaſe the Hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Court ſeriouſly to ponder that there is as great a latitude between having no Biſhops at all, and having them with the tendred limitations by thoſe they call libellers; as there is betweene re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining a limited power in Biſhops, and confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:95736:3"/>the Biſhops in the exorbitant authority and greatneſſe of Government as it is eſtabliſhed in <hi>England:</hi> which Government God forbid it were retained, being as it is conceived by the moſt learned, pious, and judicious of the land moſt Antichriſtian, and attended with more evill then the quire aboliſhing of Epiſcopacie can prove hurtfull, and of dangerous conſequence; and that for theſe reaſons and grounds follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</p>
            <p n="1">I. Epiſcopall Government as it is eſtabliſhed in <hi>England,</hi> is a continuation of the height of pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er and juriſdiction, which in the darkeſt times of Popery the Pope hath uſurped by his Biſhops and Abbots farre beyond the footing, he ever tooke in <hi>France, Spaine,</hi> or <hi>Germany.</hi> Therefore what the Authour of the remo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtrance alleadgeth of the ancientneſſe of Epiſcopacie, and of its con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance hitherto 1500. yeares is vaine and fri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valous, for the Roman Church upon the ſame ground or pleading of antitiquitie makes her he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſies and abominations warantable.</p>
            <p n="2">II. The Biſhops inſtitution and inthroniſing is altogether repugnant and contrary to the lawes and cuſtomes of the Primitive Church, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the conſtitutions of the Prime Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Emperours, who ordained that the people joyntly with the inferiour Cleargie ſhould pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent to the Emperour a catalogue of the moſt pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and learned men of the Dioceſſe, and the
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:95736:4"/>man that the Emperour was to pitch upon, be inveſted with the function of a Biſhop: for proofe thereof reade the conſtitutions of <hi>Charles</hi> the great; <hi>Lewis</hi> the godly, <hi>Gregory</hi> the great, <hi>Gela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſius</hi> and others.</p>
            <p n="3">III. The height and ſuperiority of place that Biſhops hold, is one of the greateſt reliques of the Popiſh tyranny in <hi>England,</hi> which is moſt unfit in Miniſters of the Goſpel, repugnant to the cuſtomes of other Nations, &amp; to the diſtance, yea rather neareneſſe of Office and dignity, that ought to be betweene. Biſhops and Miniſters. It is not heard but in <hi>England</hi> that Chancellors or Lord Keepers take place after Arch-Biſhops, while o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Miniſters are ſo farre inferiour and diſtant from them, as a Prince from a poore tenant or a high ſumptuous palace from a poore thatcht cot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage.</p>
            <p n="4">IIII. The Biſhops ſole exerciſe of Iuriſdicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is ſuch, as the like was never heard in any Court of juſtice, and is repugnant to reaſon and naturall equity, and cannot bee but an appendice derived from the ſonne of perdition, that arro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gates to himſelfe an unerring ſole power: The Kings Bench, Common-pleas, &amp; Exchequer, are benches of a certaine number of Iudges; The Chancellor of <hi>England</hi> hath an aſſiſtance of 12. Maſters. I would faine know when Chriſt ſaid <hi>dic Eccleſiae,</hi> if he underſtood that a Biſhop ſhould be a ſole ludge within his Dioceſſe in deciding any litigious cauſe.</p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:95736:5"/>
            <p n="5">V. Alſo the exerciſing of any Iuriſdiction by deputies, which is the prerogative of Kings, is a monſtrous uſurpation in the Biſhops of <hi>England;</hi> a ſtrange bird hatcht in no court but theirs, every judge in any other Court diſcharging his judiciall function in his own perſon. 'Tis no mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vell if they that Preach by deputies obſerve the like practiſe in keeping of Courts.</p>
            <p n="6">VI. The Biſhops jurisdiction entrenching up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the civill Magiſtrate or Iudge by their <hi>jus Pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tificium</hi> or Canon law, which the Pope left them for a legacie, ſuch are the cauſes teſtamentary and matrimoniall, is an uſurpation no leſſe bad then the former, and derogates from the holy power of Eccleſiaſticall keyes, which Biſhops aſſumed in the prime pure times of the Church.</p>
            <p n="7">VII. It were not ſo much to uſurper juriſdicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, if the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> lawes were but ſound, and their legall proceeding juſt: But their High Commiſſion, the oath <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>x officio,</hi> the horrible abuſe of excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication, the commutations of bodily penance into pecuniary, their hinderances of prohibitions, ſtopping the courſe of law, their determining of tithes &amp; poſſeſſions of livings by a <hi>Quare imped it,</hi> are as many pockie eye-ſores, which deface the holy calling of Biſhops, and make them, though their firſt inſtitution had beene of Divine right, to be now leſſe then of humane inſtitution.</p>
            <p n="8">VIII. Their not depending on any free Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſticall aſſembly is as much or more then the Papiſts aſcribe to the Pope, who by many of them is thought inferiour to the councell &amp; cenſurable by it.</p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:95736:6"/>
            <p n="9">IX. Their Viſitations are apiſh and counterfet imitations of the ancient Synods, which are dege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerated into receits of Cuſtome, as paying for Licences, Procurations, Benevolences, Synodalls, and the like. <hi>Nihil eſt quod curia Epiſcoporum non vendat, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="10">X. Their Convocations or Synods are little better; where <hi>deputati ſunt deputantes,</hi> the depu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties are deputing; where in moſt of the mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of it, there is no free choiſe of election; but Biſhops, Deanes, and Arch-deacons have right to ſit by their place and office: where thoſe of the lower Houſe are like ſo manie ſtockes, that have no motion, but as they are carried by the members of the ſphere of the higher houſe.</p>
            <p>Who ever ſhall reade <hi>Matthaeus Paris</hi> and <hi>Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thaeus Weſtmonaſterienſis;</hi> and view the disfi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gured face of the Church of England under <hi>Henry</hi> the ſecond, <hi>Iohn,</hi> &amp; <hi>Henry</hi> the third, Kings of England, will acknowledge that the Pope had more power and jurisdiction in England in the perſons of his Biſhops and Abbots, then in any other Kingdome, and will not wonder, if Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops have hitherto kept poſſeſſion, though they hold no more of the Pope; nor will he eaſily be perſwaded, that that governement is of Divine or Apoſtolicall inſtitution, which hath ever beene contrary to the conſtitutions of the ancient Church, and to Imperiall lawes, and repugnant to the proceedings of all Courts of Iuſtice, and common equity and ſence.</p>
            <p>Theſe ten grounds or reaſons which are rockie for
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:95736:7"/>upholding this aſſertion, <hi>that Epiſcopall Engliſh go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment is Antichriſtian:</hi> are ſandie under the ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructure of the Authour of the Remonſtrance, for who doubts but an Eccleſiaſticall Governement that is ſuch, cannot bee pleaded to be unalterable, and not to bee removed, though it were never ſo ancient, ſince there is no preſcription againſt Chriſt and the Apoſtles inſtitution, and that the number of yeares cannot make a lye to bee a truth; yea rather many things are worſe by age, and an old man hath no more the beeing of man, then a young man; and a common-wealth no more then a Church is nothing the better for to be of an an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cienter ſtanding. But as it is vaine and out of the queſtion, to prove Epiſcopacie to bee of Divine right, and to have continued ſo many hundred yeares, and to call unjuſt and weake the clamours of thoſe that cry downe Epiſcopacie; likewiſe it is no leſſe loſt labour to goe about to perſwade the Honorable Houſe with ſuch earneſtneſſe not to give way to the change of Epiſcopacy, which hath its pedegree from the Apoſtles: for I know none of them that cry downe ſuch an Epiſcopacie, or giveth his conſcent to pull it up, few or none of them beleeving that the Epiſcopall governe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment as it is eſtabliſhed in England is derived from the Apoſtles, who ever affirmes, that Prieſts are by Divine right, will not conſequently evince Divine right in the function of the Romiſh Prieſts: The like may I ſay of Epiſcopall governement of theſe times, in reference to that in the times of the Primitive Church:</p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:95736:8"/>
            <p>As the Remonſtrancers ſuperſtructure is like to be tottering, if it be grounded upon that ſuppoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that Engliſh Epiſcopall governement is Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtolicall, ſo will it bee like to fall, having no better ground then he layes downe, viz. That Epiſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacy, or the eminent ſuperiority of Biſhops above their fellow Presbyters in the power of ordinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and juriſdiction is of Divine inſtitution, and that that ſpirituall power hath beene by Apoſtoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call authoritie delegated unto <hi>Timothy</hi> and <hi>Titus,</hi> and to the Angells of the Church of <hi>Aſia;</hi> Touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Timothy,</hi> it is a wonder that Saint <hi>Paul</hi> writing to the Epheſians doth not ſo much as once make mention of him; far is he to enjoyne him to keepe reſidence in his Dioceſſe, where it is like hee made no great reſidence, being upon every occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion ſent from place to place by the appointment of Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> and it appeareth by <hi>Ireneus, Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cephorus,</hi> and <hi>Euſebius,</hi> that <hi>John</hi> the Apoſtle im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately after the councell of the Apoſtles, <hi>Act</hi> the 15 did governe the Church of <hi>Epheſus,</hi> untill the dayes of <hi>Trajan</hi> the Emperour: I might alſo wonder that S. <hi>Paul,</hi> who had a cooperatour in moſt things he did or wrote, would ordaine Elders in <hi>Epheſus,</hi> when they had at hand their <hi>Dioceſan</hi> Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop appointed for that work, neither by the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels of the ſeven <hi>Aſian</hi> Churches are meant ſeven ſeverall Dioceſan Biſhops; for the things ſpoken to a ſingle Angel are ſaid to him under that title, in the name of all the flocke, within the precinct of one particular Church or congregation. Thus the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels <hi>Geneſ.</hi> 32. v. 1. who met <hi>Jacob,</hi> are in the 46. chap. verſe 16. included in one Angel. And it
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:95736:9"/>is the expoſition of <hi>Calvin Pſal.</hi> 43. v. 7. that by a ſingle Angel pitching his campe for the defence of the faithfull, more then one, yea all the good Angels are underſtood: I ſay more that it is verie likelie that by the Angel of one Church, not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the Elders of that one Church are underſtood, but alſo the whole Church it ſelfe; elſe it will follow that for the ſinne of one Biſhop or a few Miniſters, if they had not repented the whole con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation had deſerved to be bereaved of the light of the Goſpel, and the words <hi>ſome of you,</hi> in the 2. chap. verſe 10. whether they inſinuate the whole Church, or the Paſtors of the Church, doe ſhew, they cannot be underſtood of one ſingle Angel or Miniſter.</p>
            <p>In the next place, the Author of the Remon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrance ſaith in deriſion of the French diſcipline, that Lay-Elders till this age had never any foot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the Chriſtian Church, I will not ſtand reaſoning what great neede there is of Laymen to bee ſharers with the Paſtors in the adminiſtration of the Churches diſcipline: onely to make good, that ſuch Lay Presbyters are grounded upon Scripture, it is cleare out of the words of the <hi>Acts</hi> chap. 15. verſe 22. <hi>It pleaſeth the Apoſtles, the El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, with the whole Church.</hi> By <hi>the whole Church</hi> either the whole company of Elders, or the chiefe of the people, if not the whole Chriſtian congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation preſent at <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> is underſtood. The former cannot be, elſe by an uncouth tautologie in one little verſe, the Elders were ſaid to have met with Elders. It followes then, that by <hi>the whole Church</hi> others be meant beſides Biſhops and El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders;
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:95736:10"/>It matters not much whether they bee cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Lay-Presbyters or not, as long as the thing intended is granted, <hi>viz.</hi> that the Laicke congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation may meddle in Churches affaires, and give councell and aſſiſtance to the Paſtors and bee as well as they arbiters and cenſurers of errors and diſorders. For further proofe thereof in the 14 of the <hi>Acts</hi> verſe 23. though the Engliſh verſion hath, <hi>When they had ordained Elders,</hi> the Greeke <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> beares as much, as that Elders were ordained by the adviſe of the congregation. Again in the 6. of the <hi>Acts,</hi> the whole multitude of Diſciples is ſaid to have choſen the ſeven Deacons of whom Saint <hi>Steven</hi> was one. That by the multitude of the Diſciples others are meant then the company of the Elders, it is manifeſt by the ninth of the <hi>Acts,</hi> verſe 39. where <hi>Tabitha</hi> a woman is called an ancient Diſciple: And by the eleventh chap. verſe 26. where it is ſaid that the Diſciples were firſt called Chriſtians in <hi>Antioch;</hi> The appellations of Diſciples and Chriſtians being promiſcuouſly uſed; beſides we ſee in the election of the Apoſtle <hi>Matthias,</hi> not onely the Apoſtles, but the whole congregation which was of 120. had vote and voice. Good Lord ſhall one of few Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops in our dayes vindicate more to themſelves then the Apoſtles themſelves did; though the leaſt of the Apoſtles were better gifted, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowed with more power, then all the Biſhops of the Chriſtian World put together. Now adayes the greateſt part of the Church is counted no Church, and it remaineth that mens ſoules ſhould
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:95736:11"/>be pinned up within three or foure mens Lawne-ſleeves. But which is moſt ſtrange, thoſe that quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rell ſo much about Lay-Elders, ſee not or will not ſee, that what they except againſt the reformed Churches out of <hi>England,</hi> is even practiſed in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> in the offices of Chancellors, Commiſſaries, Officials, Regiſters, Apparitors, &amp; ſuch like Graſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoppers, with that onely difference, that theſe make a ſale of holy things, and rend in two the ſeameleſſe coate of Chriſt, they often drawing it one way, and the Biſhops another way. But the Lay-Presbyters ſo much jeered at by the Remon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrancer both live in good amitie with the Paſtors, and diſcharge their places <hi>gratis.</hi> I ſay more, it was never heard in France or in the Low Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries, that Lay-Elders did vindicate ſo much to themſelves of the power of the Eccleſiaſticall keys, as the Biſhops Chancellors have of late u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurped in pronouncing ſentence of excommunica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and abſolution without the knowledge, and againſt the intent of the Biſhop. It is alſo a great wounding of the Kings authority to debarre Lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men from medling in Churches affaires; for who is it that doth not know, that our dreadfull King is a Layman, and that the Chriſtian Magiſtrate can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be kept from having a hand in the adminiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Church without implicitely wounding through their ſide, the head of the Chriſtian Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate.</p>
            <p>To ſupport more ſtrongly the governement of the Church in <hi>England</hi> by Biſhops, hee bringeth the aſſent and teſtimonie of <hi>Spanhemius</hi> a learned
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:95736:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>Profeſſion in <hi>Geneva.</hi> I expected the teſtimonie of many more Divines. To which I anſwer, that <hi>Spanhemius</hi> and many more as <hi>Moulin, Rivet, Chamier,</hi> had likewiſe in reverend eſteeme Epiſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacy in the Church of God, and therefore had no reaſon to condemne Epiſcopacie, or to fall out with the pious &amp; learned men that were inveſted with it, ſuch are thoſe yet living <hi>Morton, Davenant, Hall, Williams, Potter,</hi> and the incomparable Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate of <hi>Ireland,</hi> who do not ſtretch their power to the extent of their high Juriſdiction as it is e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtabliſhed in <hi>England,</hi> which I make no queſtion is avowed by all the orthodoxe Paſtors out of <hi>England</hi> to be a branch of that kingdome of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſt, that had taken ſo deepe root in <hi>England:</hi> This man make <hi>Spanhemius</hi> more inſenſible then a ſtone, had hee approved the uncharitableneſſe and the bitter venim and foule aſperſions that were caſt upon the reformed <hi>French</hi> Churches and particularly upon <hi>Geneva</hi> by thoſe Biſhops, and others who lately ſate at the ſterne of the Churches government. The Archbiſhop <hi>Laude</hi> hath more then once called <hi>Calvin</hi> a raſcall, and the <hi>Geneuian</hi> lay Presbiters, a new fangled deviſe of <hi>Calvin,</hi> leaving to ſpeake how he vilifies with baſe termes, other Reverend <hi>French</hi> Divines; in his Epiſtle to the King before the <hi>opuſcula poſthu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma</hi> of Biſhop <hi>Andrewes,</hi> hee gives that report of <hi>Peter Moulin</hi> that hee is <hi>Theol gus non indoctus &amp; acutus ſatis. A Diuine not vnlearned and reaſonable acute.</hi> Neither doth he ſpare his owne, as <hi>Cran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer,</hi> and <hi>Latimer,</hi> calling them the Zelotes of
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:95736:13"/>Queene <hi>Maries</hi> daies. Biſhop <hi>Mountague</hi> in his <hi>Apparatus</hi> and elſe where, calles the <hi>Geneuians</hi> by no other name then <hi>Jnnovators,</hi> and traduceth them and their followers, ſuch as <hi>Scaliger, Paraeus</hi> and <hi>Caluiſius,</hi> as a packe of Shiſmatickes, and brame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe raſcalls: The like dealing have they with Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop <hi>Wren, Pierce, Manwaring, Heylin, Pocklington, Couſin,</hi> and the like; what charitable encertaine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment judge ye, may <hi>Genevâs</hi> Church finde among ſuch men, ſince one of the beſt Biſhops of <hi>England</hi> is reported to have given that judgement of their diſcipline, that it is fit onely for tradeſmen and beggers: In that the charitie of <hi>Spanhemius</hi> and others reformed Divines beyond the ſeas is to be commended, that they have not reviled againe thoſe that reviled them, and following the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of God ſaying to <hi>Abraham,</hi> hee would not deſtroy the whole citie for tens ſake; they have for the inchoate reformation ſake in the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and for the reſpect they beare to a little number of well deſerving Biſhops and others, paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed over the invectives and inſolences of that great ſtreame of corrupt men, that went currant under the name of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Church, &amp; as they have heartily pittied their rage, ſo have they forgiven them their uncharitableneſſe. Other men that have not been ſo much intereſſed in our Churches, have not diſſembled what they thought of our <hi>Engliſh</hi> Epiſcopall governement. The words of <hi>Padre Paulo Sarpio venetian</hi> in his Epiſtle to <hi>James Leſchaſſerius</hi> Counſellor at <hi>Paris</hi> in the yeare 1609. are wonderfull remarkable, and the more,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:95736:14"/>becauſe they are a prediction of what came to paſſe in <hi>England; J am afraid in the behalfe of the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh of that great power of Biſhops, though under a King, J have it in ſuſpicion, when they ſhall meete with a King, of that goodneſſe as they will thinke it eaſie to work upon him, or ſhall have an Archbiſhop of an high ſpirit, the Royall authoritie ſhall be wounded, and Biſhops will aſpire to an abſolute domination: Me thinkes I ſee a horſe ſadled in England, and J gueſſe that the old rider ſhall get on his backe: But all theſe things depend on the Divine Providence.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Next our Remonſtrancer exhorteth with more modeſtie then reaſon, the high Court not to pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh the offences and ſcandalls of the inferiour Cleargie, leaving off verie diſcreetly to ſpeake, off the monſtruous enormities of which the ſuperiour Cleargy is guilty. Good Lord ſir, you will give leave to a man that hath beene unjuſtly gagg'd long, at the firſt libertie given, to cry out and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaine of the wrong he hath received: or if ſome ſinnes of their nature are crying, would you have them kept under aſhes, that they may afterwards breake with fiercer violence: or how can the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ladie be cured till it be laid open and ſearcht to the bottome; That the body of this Church is very craſie and ſicke, wee that are the members ſmart for it. To beginne at the head, our Remonſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer ſaith: it is no marvell, if among 12 Apoſtles there bee one <hi>Judas;</hi> but rather may wee expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtulate to our great hearts greife, that of 12 rulers of the Church there is hardly one that is right and ſound: And no wonder if an Antichriſtian Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipline
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:95736:15"/>as I proved afore, brings up men, whoſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide, doctrine and life is ſutable to the outſide. The greateſt part of Deanes, Archdeacons, and all thoſe that are compriſed under the, &amp;c. of the oath are gone out of the way: The fountaines of learning are poyſoned with hereſies and infected with Popery: of late no other Doctrine but Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh &amp; Arminian was licenſed to ſee light, no bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die durſt call the Pope Antichriſt, or the Romiſh Church the falſe Church, and the writings of the Arch-Biſhop of Canterbury, of Biſhop <hi>Mountagu,</hi> the Sermons of <hi>Manwaring,</hi> the bookes of <hi>Heylin, Pocklington, Coſin,</hi> and the like, are flat Popery. And no wonder therefore if they maintaine ſtiffely that the Engliſh Church is not ſeparated from the Roman, &amp; that they both agree in the fundamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall points of Religion. The power of Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing hath beene of late reduced to outward geſtures and bowings towards the Eaſt or Altar, and the myſterie of inquirie, which is the good worke in hand of <hi>Heylin</hi> had got already to a great pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſe: Theſe being the great maladies of the Church, farre be it from that high and juſt Court not to heare or to ſmother the grievances of the Churche, and by a cruell kindneſſe, rather let a man be drowned, then to take him by the haires for feare of hurting him.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
